so what do you think about the thoughts
that having pets increases ones
attachments
well the brief answer it's
things in the world are not your
attachment it's your attitude towards
the things in the world the same sense
the Buddha said beautiful things in the
world or not are not men sensuality
desire and lust towards those things
that sensuality is there so people
blaming things for their attachment
means people not seeing where the
attachment is so as long as you blame
things for attachment you're gonna be
attached because the most natural
response is when people think I must
give up the attachment is to throw away
all my possessions and get rid of
everything but that's not freeing you
from attachment that's just obscuring
your attitude that you had towards those
things which means when something else
comes your way you're gonna be attached
to it because you haven't undermined
that a mental stance of appropriation so
in terms of pets or family members
parents like your attachment is is is
your emotional dependence upon those
things being present in the world not
those things in the world because if
truly you would need to get rid of the
stuff to be free from attachment means
you need to go and destroy the whole
world to be free from attachment to the
world but that's not how it works
there are some some things some
relationships not worthy of having yeah
yeah well sensuality in general so like
if you if you want to have pets in this
particular example well before you do
ask yourself why are you are you having
pets because you generally want to help
animals oh you're having pets because
you're feeling lonely or bored or you
need you need excitement or some novelty
or just a cute little pet with cheese
but most people don't think this through
that's why I like the shelters are full
of abandoned animals in the West because
people will take them in in a spur of a
moment and then afterwards basically
when that kind of novelty runs out you
realize it's it's it's to demand it too
much care till it takes too much time
too much effort so much responsibility
then you just give them what took place
is that sort of provided but really what
you do is just make it someone else's
problem and that all could have been
prevented if you if you were a bit more
self reflexive before you commit it
obviously you have like things that make
your parents or your family for example
you have no choice you can't give them
away and so that's why you sometimes you
and so that's why you sometimes you
bound with things that kind of create
attachment for you but it doesn't mean
that you're not responsible for the
attachment part yeah you're no
responsible for being paired with these
people or those disks your family or so
on but you are responsible if you're
emotionally attached upon it but if you
think that you can free yourself from
attachment just by dismissing these
people or these things in the world your
soleus heaven like serious the mistake
in lessening the attachment giving it up
it's much subtler than that so if
somebody has a pet and I see that they
are quite emotionally attached to it
what should I do they want to treat
himself well basically they should they
should contemplate the death of that pet
as much as they can without abandoning
it without stopping like withdrawing
care for it and helping it but you just
have to keep reminding yourself to the
point of view where you become sort of
when you go emotionally above it above
the thought that this thing that is this
pet this friend or whatever whatever
attitude you have towards it it's gonna
go you will go you might die you in the
forest and it will it will it's
unpleasant that's where people are kind
of either/or
either I'll be fully invested
emotionally or are completely dismissive
and throw it away and not having to do
it because I'm afraid of my attachment
the fact that you're a favor I get
attached means you're not free from
possibility of that we means you're not
free from nature of attachment and
that's the problem that's not a problem
and like you you might you can give away
the pet tell the other things you're
then attached attached to so really you
want a wreckin is a problem and then see
okay there are certain things that are
not necessary a certain degree of
involvement is not necessary and you've
been doing it purely out of attachment
now when you became aware of the
attachment you will naturally be draw
yourself to a certain degree but there
is no blanket rule how much you must be
withdrawn from the world and from your
engagements different people measure
these things differently the engagement
means different things for them also
some people can take more of it some
people can't so that that should not be
the criteria like how many pets you have
for example or how many charities you
support no Cristina should be how much
of the attachment is there regardless
and in regard to animals still do you
think it's best to leave them alone but
interfere as a human being I don't think
there is universal law you can do
whatever you like basically it doesn't
mean you won't pay the price for it yeah
if you're in a position to help why
wouldn't you I mean even the Buddha
himself said giving even to an animal or
not even to a specific animal just
throwing away food and saying may those
animals and creatures that feed on this
food feed on this food that I've thrown
away that will bring you merit and and
sort of like a good reward for your
actions let alone let alone helping
helping helping humans or helping great
a number of animals and so on but yeah
you don't have to do it like you must
help you don't but aren't they some
people think that animals happier when I
not around human beings yes they might
think that and what they should do is
ask themselves why do they think that
and you're probably gonna find out that
they think it because they want to find
the justification for them not helping
animals in the first place like when
they are in position to do when they
wouldn't even necessarily be attached to
it even to help them and they still
don't do it and then they would find out
well that's whatever they say that's
their karma they deserve it basically oh
and they're just ridiculous even if they
do deserve it
that still has nothing to do with you
choosing to not help somebody in need of
help animal or human now if you don't
help me you don't have to feel guilty
it's it's you know it's really up to you
to do whatever you want but if your self
honesty and if you question your motives
you will see that usually not helping is
rooted in unwholesome motives neither
ill-will or dismissal can be bother
can't and I don't care or too lazy or
whatever and if you're aware of it you
wouldn't want it
what about neutering sorry what about
you Tony
you drink the anonymous of your pets to
their content the country well of course
now to answer the question obviously it
would depends what what what point of
view come from but obviously as as
somebody who practices the Dhamma and
the goodies person it's probably the
best thing you can do to an animal
because animals stay animals as in they
remain bound to central animal central
realm because all the thoughts all the
reactions revolve around senses around
animal intentions around cravings
sexuality food fighting it is constantly
driven and because of that it's so hard
and greatest asks of the animal Arriba
and that's what the Buddha said it takes
like a blind and similar for blind
turtle coming up to the top of the sea
of the ocean once every 500 years and
there is a yoga a piece of wood with a
hole in it it's been sort of thrown and
floating left-to-right thrown by the
winds in the way and this is blind
turtle that comes from the bottom once
500 years has a greater chance of
sticking its head through that hole in
that little piece of wood is being
thrown constantly then a being that has
fallen into an animal realm has a chance
of coming back to human realm
why because you look at them whatever
they do it's bound with the animal realm
entirely so they cannot have things sort
of like a loftier nature they will then
result in a in a High River
and so why neutering is good is because
animals can't restrain themselves the
only way they can destroy themselves if
is if that's that restraint is placed
externally mind you that's true for most
of humans but we are speaking about
animals so basically the lucky animal is
the one that has proper restraint placed
upon it externally as in fire humans not
like violence no violence no so like
neutering them as we've done with these
dogs you saw the massive difference is like
you saw the massive difference is like
they don't think about sexuality enough
and you do remember when they did think
about it or like a madness will come
over the mind which means all the
actions they will be committing on
account of it are very very unwholesome
and they have no they don't have enough
self reflection to see that so in a way
they're big
victims were they're victims of their
own actions and that's why keeps
perpetuating itself so the lucky dog for
example or a cat or whatever the one
that you neuter means you took that very
powerful unwholesome dimension out of
their existence basically sexuality
craving fighting I mean raping it's
horrible like when they get into the
mating the heat
it's just violence when you look on the
roads and streets and they lose
perspective as well completely come back
malnourished ripped apart because
they're fighting for dominance you know
everything just unwholesome on top of
the unwholesome and now you new to them
and that whole dimension is gone they
can't even think about it anymore let
alone act upon it so you could see that
in a animal realm which could be
considered a darker realm as in all the
actions are bound with sensuality in
your will and craving and fear and so on
having an absence of the same amount of
bad actions can actually mean a lot of
positive in the same sense with the
Buddha said in the dark realms even just
like a fleeting thought a positive
thought in even in even very fleeting in
the nature can mean a lot why because
there isn't any so we really stand out
and if you then bring those those beings
back up to higher realms where they
can't become aware of the self
refraction and consequently that's how they would
and consequently that's how they would
have said the people who live their life
unrestrained don't even keep the Five
Precepts and basically just follow every
single desire that they have scratched
each when every reaches they're no
different in animals and usually that's
the realm they're heading their behavior
is taking that to them then you just
react upon any impulse becomes your way
and completely are unaware due to your
own obscuring unaware of the
responsibilities that you actually
inherently carry for your own choices
and your own freedom so that's I mean
people don't have to help anyone but you
should really ask yourself if you choose
not to help well ask yourself why why
did you make that choice why was it
routine which is really carelessness
laziness hatred whatever defined it up
so is there any other way that you could
help animals if you wanted to open
neutral I mean you might want to do that
right well I think obviously just
providing like feeding them for example
means they'll be less on that verge of
hunger they will they will make them
edgy and and then in a fighting mode and
ingredie and stealing and so on these
are all some things sure vaccinations so
you'll help them obviously by like if
you can buy shelter providing shelter
providing medicine providing food then
if you have the ability trained them a
bit just make them wait for the food
literally that's something that people
could benefit from I eat whenever I feel
an urge to put something my mouth place
if not when I'm hungry and actually the
Buddha did say that in one of the
suitors there is some regard animals are
actually more virtuous than most of the
like the contemporary people at the time
said they would mate only when there was
basically a season when a female would
be in the season but at the time and
what I was saying that he would have
these days rich people with having like
manifold many wives and just constantly
having sexual intercourse left and right
without a purpose just so purpose was
sent
the other thing that the Buddha did say
was in regards to the same tour Sutra
was the yet like the animals would eat
when they're hungry the dogs but then
you had people like like a crowing
wealth and just not sharing and just
eating whenever they wanted just
hoarding it being greedy basically so in
that regard animals are more restrained
but obviously you know sexuality is a
big part in every being sort of life and
certainly can be a great motivator which
always results in unwholesome
proliferation of desire which is then
responsible for your rebirth in actions
you commit an account of it so so dojust
just helping animals in that sense you
would basically prevent the whole the
whole domain of attachment for them on
account of which you'll be doing lots or
lots of unwholesome actions now given
for a female dog well I mean first of
all you help her not going through that
whole process of being physically
gang-raped by the bunch of where a pack
of dogs
Meucci so how you might not happen when
people are kind of carefully breeding
dogs but when you look out in the road
like ten males and it's just battlefield
in two weeks for two weeks they're just
crying in a beautiful and then on top of
it puppies children are the greatest
attachment and it's no different for
animals so people think are you
depriving these animals of happiness
yeah well their happiness is just like
one percent on top of the 99 percent of
pain and exposure to paint
but not just that she can barely fend
for herself and provide for herself like
a stray dog for example as a six puppies
to feed and you see that when you see
the stray dog with puppies when she
starts breastfeeding it just turns into
this completely invented sort of
skeleton but within a week because they
don't get enough and then you think
that's Pleasant
it's pleasant for the dog and for the
puppet it is it's just completely the
opposite just torture and most as
puppies will end up dying and and
probably the mother as well if not if
she doesn't die clearly it's gonna take
a like half a year to recover to the fur
back and health back by which time she's
gonna get pregnant again and then again
and it's just a constant sort of been
subjected to just the constant pressure
and striving and greed here and fighting
yeah and you remove that and it's just a
happy dog
and what if what if your dogs gets a get
very sick and one of their mind a lot of
pain there's no cure
would you consider euthanasia we're all
gonna die anyway the thing if a dog were
to have a choice to do it itself yeah I
would interfere with it either but they
don't which means you'll be killing it
even if there is it a lot of pain
doesn't matter because the pains that
you can perceive someone else dying
might not be anything in comparison to
the pains of a being actually dying in
other words like he might look painful
but it's still alive but when actually
starts dying
that's the worst type of pain and that
is according to the Buddha but usually
people judge this situation based on how
they feel or I can bear to watch this so
I'll kill it
compassionately I'll put it out of my
misery pretty much yeah I'll put it out of my
pretty much yeah I'll put it out of my
misery yeah that's that's how it should
read
I mean again you can do whatever you
want but don't deceive yourself you are
killing it but what about like dog
shelters like they get always stray dogs
yeah okay now Kelly twenty thousand
dollars they're killing it but I mean
they obviously they're responsible for
the act of gassing them and whatever
means they use but whoever gives the
doctor shelter is also responsible for
killing them if then they're being
killed because they wouldn't a vendor
being killed if you didn't put him in a
shelter their kills dogs so that's for
me think twice before you actually
choose to act and commit and do things
in any area of life but people's
judgment basically it's usually
emotional which some reader judgment
it's more a reaction I want this I have
it and then I'm not only going to look
at the reasons for having it I'm not
going to stop and think about and maybe
be patient and see if I change my mind
or if I really thought this through as
well just for the pets in general in
general that's the attitude
another question that usually comes up a
lot of people
how can monastics he was drawn from
sensual pleasures if they're using the
Internet
the internet for it's very sensual thing
right so how could you have to use the
Internet yeah you use it for that particular
yeah you use it for that particular
reason basically Internet is a tool so
if you use tool to gain sensuality yeah
but you don't blame the tool you blame
your own sensual intentions and your own
central actions you cannot engage in
sensuality without having sort of we
have perceived it as as essential as a
sensual desire as a central outcome that
you want to pursue
which means sensuality is always
intentional you can't accidentally
stumble like engage in sensuality so the
question here it's not like whether you
should is internet or not the question
is are you restrained or not if you're
not restrained then yeah you should
proceed these circumstances they might
tempt you further and then you avoid it
but even then you don't place
responsibility on avoidance of these
things because the real problem is you
not just having a pooted sensuality so
you might avoid internet all you want
but you can still spend your time with
sensual thoughts central cravings living
on top of mountain and be bound by it
you may wonder you have to use the
Internet well sooner or later something will
well sooner or later something will
happen were you going to be exposed to
things they used to cause you so
basically sensual desire and you're
gonna have it again because you haven't
done anything about it you can't spend
your whole life in hiding and that was
that that very nice suit that this
simile will debate the deer herd that
the Buddha talks about well like most
people would the hunter place is the the
the food that has a bait in it and
that's basically like a description of a
simile for sensuality it baits you to
become sort of engaged with it and
attach just because of that promised
pleasure so the most people would be
sort of careless and they'll just be
eating it together with a bait they
would even see it as a problem they
won't even see the bait and it's a group
of people who recognize that and then
say well okay we need to restrain
ourselves because that's basically oh
but they can't draw a line between food
and debate so then they dismiss the
entire domain
food and there's what I said they're
like a deer herd that runs on top of
mountain and then they live lives there
but sooner or later the food will
whatever they've been living on in the
mountain will dry out and then they will
come back to the same environment that
they despised and they would eat
carelessly they wouldn't see the bait
and they would remain the same as the
first herd and then the third one would
be basically the one who's seen the
first scene the second and then they
realize actually we must not shun them
the food you just have to learn how to
eat it carefully without engaging with
the bait without being hooked and that's
the whole point
but that refers to basically avoiding
sensuality not like flirting with
sensuality and carefully so you don't
get no flirting with sensuality means
you basically already hold but learning
how to it carefully or in other words
learning how to be restrained and seeing
where your responsibility is because
that's what mean like people would blame
the food blame the internet blame this
blame the city blame the environment but
that's not a problem the problem is your
attitude of sensuality in regard to it
so if you recognize that that's on you
you exercise restraint to the right
degree and then you could see generally
oh this is a tool this can be used
awesomely obviously this cannot be used
homes also lay things like sexual
intercourses they're fully already
perverted by the desire which means you
can't do it rightly you have to abandon
it all together
so if a person does have problems with
the distraint show minimize your
exposure to things that are challenging
you but don't project your
responsibility onto those things it's a
new you have to see it your weakness
well exactly good to see it and then you
have to see what what the problem is the
problem is not the Internet the problem
is not the central object the problem is
your sensuality in regard to it and
you're not gonna approve that just by
dismissing the central object or the
object that could potentially result in
central outcome and if you start
clarifying that then yeah then you are
developing enough space basically to see
and to move about without taking things
up in central man
when she's caught you become quite
strong because you can withstand the
possibilities well not just withstand
you actually have rooted the possibility
of you centrally engaging in central
possibilities it's and that's when you
know you're beyond sensuality it's like
no amount of central objects would
become a temptation anymore
because the mind has fully seen and
discerned the danger of sensuality and
the inherent basically repulsiveness of
it being a victim to your own desire you
fully understood that and that's and by
doing so you have abandoned it so then
you can't actually engage with it intent
like it's inconceivable the Buddha would
say it's like as if a man would sort of
eat some delicious food and then he
would vomit it out and that would he
have a desire to eat that vomit again he
just wouldn't it's inconceivable they
repelled by the thought of it
she said earlier about how to overcome
attachments like to your dogs to pets
amis there to contemplate the the
possibility inevitable possibility of
their dead into free from the touch when
I say contemplate I mean allow yourself
to emotionally feel the significance of
those things not like explain to
yourself just basically to appease your
own emotional disturbance and the
thought of you peel your favorite pet
down or something no the law of the old
and then you start explain though you
actually want to take it on that
emotional level basically to not be
afraid to feel the death of the loved
ones and they will basically pressure
your mind into growth the man will have
to grow out of it or it will have to
succumb to it it reminds me of what
you're saying this morning about being
intoxicated with youth
it's it's but thank you for granting
your own life you start taking for
granted lives of other things beings
with animals or humans which means death
even an ocean of it is gonna be
frightening to you to your emotional
life delivery it's gonna be a challenge
so unless you recognize that as a
problem you can't sort of grow out you can't
you can't sort of grow out you can't
develop yourself out of it
you just can't because you've gone all
of your efforts will be about covering
it up where we all die there's none of
that all of that is done just to prevent
you from taking it on personally but if
you if you start questioning basically
just well the validity of that
assumption like why do I mean yeah we
will all die so why don't I imagine that
I might be dead by this afternoon or
maybe even tomorrow like why would I why
would I just assume that my life is
ahead of me or my health or my youth
and if you start questioning these
things on the level of of yourself means
you are automatically affecting any
attachment that you have depending upon
those things in regard to others in
other words if you become fully aware of
your own mortality you cannot be
attached to other person's life does it
mean you become like a brand of livius
robotic creature now you're still full
of air of the significance of life of
helping animals or caring after people
or whatever but none of that causes that
the emotional intoxication of off
assumption that this will last forever
which means when it changes when it goes
away different to the way you expected
it and hopeful you won't be affected by
it your perspective will remain
basically undiminished you just will not
change because it wasn't dependent upon
that anymore and that the true meaning
will be free from attachment and freedom
not like not recognizing the
significance of it you know dying loved
ones or something like that
no on the country being fully able to
let it arise to the extent he wants to
rise and you won't have to do anything
about it you don't have to jump into
grief break down into tears nothing
you're able to hold it and keep
perspective in regard to it as those
enlightened people in the searchers
would say like how could it be otherwise
when they were facing somebody dying the
good friend or mother father whatever it
would be just like like how could it be
otherwise how could a thing that has a
reason not die it's no surprise doesn't
surprise no it's what it's surprising to think
no it's what it's surprising to think
they can be otherwise
that's a surprise for those who cannot
think that anything
it's very much what Stowe is very much
in this think about premeditate yeah
think about death
think about loss of house AG yes not
surprised minute the right thought
people people think the right thought
will come out to prevent is that of some
sort of magical experience no right
thought will come up if you stop
engaging nurturing and maintaining the
wrong foot and the wrong thought is
anything to greed aversion delusion any
thoughts that it's based upon assumption
that perpetuates these gratuitous
assumptions and intoxications
meet your life which your health I mean
people think just like when they're help
do you think you're never gonna get sick
and then just the thought that you might
get sick freaks you out all the way it's
like nothing there's no no no safe zone
in between so like when people get a flu
they just full-on panic they want every
medicine from the shelf doctor to give
them just just to get rid of this
discomfort because it's threatening to
my existential assumption of what an
indefinite health record pimple in the
face oh yeah yeah sure sure a pimple on
the face or around this like sort of a
hair going the other way you don't wants
to go or something is just interfering
with your perception of yourself and
it's like bothering you on that
existential level no it's not like it's
not optional
you can't remain indifferent to words
you are being emotionally oppressed and
you doing it yourself basically by
maintaining those assumptions they when
then they when they're challenged by the
circumstances of the world they go
against your your your desires basically
yeah you can
remain in debt you are affected so
suffering is as they will describe in
the most general terms physically not
getting will one what what what one
wants and being paired with things that
one doesn't want in brief
basically you this five minute eyes in
your experience is a whole attachment to
it in any shape or form
that's why suffering is there
Cheryl's gonna ask this question you
touch them touching a bit is how to
improve your thinking how to make you
thinking clearer and light about the
right deeply well that's that's the
thing the first step is to to get a hint
at least that actually this might be a
valuable thing to do learn how to think
properly then if you do then you can
start looking closer at it and basically
see what is what are the things that are
sort of against right mindful thinking
essential desire is by giving into
central desire to the emotional needs
you are compromising your own reason
now some people do more some people do
less but nevertheless that's in common
to every time you give in to desire or
or need for emotional satisfaction for
central satisfaction to that degree you
compromise your reason you compromise
your mindfulness even if you're actually
contemplating in premeditating heart
engages and Chu allottee that's not done
in a trifle manner because it's not
founded upon mindfulness and
self-awareness you are projected towards
a project of sexuality or whatever else
so so recognizing what what goes against
to come composed mindful thinking clear
clear clarity is a foggy foggy obtuse or
faked whatever it's all against it so it
will anger it's it's against it engaging
in angry behavior cultivating your will
and hatred you are basically obscuring
your own perspective on yourself same
with sensuality same with distraction in
general you just want to do something
because you're bored
boredom is actually clarity and that's
where people fear it because it reveals
things but you don't want to admit to
himself yet they're always there that's
what people always need things to do is
essentially they depend upon constant
performing of action and finding meaning
in random things just to make them do
stuff because it basically keeps you
keeps you floating or so
seems if you run out of things to do if
you run out of even the most frivolous /
frivolous purpose you basically feel
like just you begin to sink but the
problem with that whole set up the whole
view is the sooner or later you won't be
able to do things and what you're gonna
have left is that we should be running
away from your whole life that's why old
age is very unpleasant the body stops
listening you lost your health you lost
your strength you don't see youth the
senses are failing you can't get
distracted now through beautiful signs
believe you can't even appreciate it
anymore it just hurts to look hurts to
hear it so present eating and what
you're left is yourself that's what
you're left with
and that's something you didn't want to
be with your whole life and that's why
you've been using the intoxication with
intoxication with health youth in life
and sensuality in general just to keep
sort of surfing on top of it without
having to face what's underneath nice letter
nice letter
clarity awareness constantly waterway
can be good painful is it boredom is
very painful foods clarity what clarity
is not painful but it reveals the
painful background and that bedroom is
painful only because you're resisting it
only because your habits of your life
the ones you've been engaging with are
the ones that are taking away from it
namely sensuality just following your
desires for granted wanting to have
whatever your desire basically directs
you directs you it and because of that
not engage in that behavior is being
painful you play to the pain of boredom
as it bordered you create the boredom
because you don't want it boredom in
itself it's not neutral so it's neutral
it's not unpleasant it's not a pleasant
or unpleasant
let's we're gonna say if you understand
neutral feeling it is felt as pleasant
you don't understand it as and if you're
still basically affecting it with
assumptions and preconceived notions and
habits of sensuality then is gonna feel
unpleasant feeling nothing is gonna feel
unpleasant he's gonna feel threatening
basically
so did you have any practices to clear
one well physically restraint not not
engaging in distracted behavior sense
restraint not not engaging in basically
like yeah you have to stop for example
drinking being careless taking drugs
because that certainly it's directly
opposed to any clarity that you can
maintain in your mind then at the same
time you also have to understand that
the real clarity comes from
understanding what clarity is not from
what feels clear that's inevitable the
beginning we all start based on how we
feel but you want to transcend that you
don't want to just be bound by how you
feel and what you deem pleasant or
unpleasant because well people don't
understand the clarity and they're just
going to be pursuing that which they
think clarity is which is that which
they deem agreeable not necessarily
understood and that's when you have
people over doing the practice of
clarity trying to catch every single
moment and things like that but that's a
contradiction in terms
you know to catch a moment you have to
be outside of the moment but if you're
outside of the moment the moment in your
experience so you're just chasing these
hollow contradictory ideas on account to
develop some clarity
so clarity is basically absence agreed a
version delusion if those things are not
present in your experience you don't
have to then get rid of whatever else
it's present cause all you care about is
the unwholesome aspect but people
usually can't can't see where the line
is so then they try to dismiss it all in
the same sense when I spoke just
internet attachment is a problem so I'll
throw away everything baby in the bottle
the whole thing
oh I'm attached to this I must destroy
it I must get rid of it I must give it
up that's why I free myself for my
attachments oh you want and the Buddha
realized that when he came to the point
of even trying to give up his own life
because thinking that's the way I didn't
give you guys it wasn't it's only gonna
result in the dying unenlightened
when he tried to stop his own breathing
place it would be so while I'm breathing
I'm helping this life that's a base of
attachment a fortune he did and he saw
through it and then he realized it
actually no this only resulted in me
being dead
not realizing so abandoned things that
are necessary to the basically full
proliferation of and carelessness in
regard to sensuality ill-will restraint
in moderation and then try to understand
that clarity don't overdo it either and
or mystified what about said
concentrating on a neutral object would
that take away all the unwholesome
objects well no because concentration
for people today means absorption and if
you absorbed into something means you're
not aware of yourself so I can develop
self reflection and self clarity if the
basic premise of yourself being present
and seeing that in the situation is not
there that's what most of the
contemporary meditation meditation
techniques are completely misleading no
doubt that the novelty experiences in
peace come out of it but that peace is
also peace and at a cost of self
reflection which means it's a it's a
peace that's peaceful only because it's
agreeable no because it's a genuine
clarity or contains wisdom it's only
because it's a find it agreeable and
that's why often it ceases to be enough
as well so then people need to do it
harder commit harder to get more of their
commit harder to get more of their
novelty best it's going to be a peaceful
feeling but that's not the peace you
want it's basically peace within the sensual
it's basically peace within the sensual
domain
and that's not peaceful
remember the power of concentration
you don't want power of concentration
you want power of reflection and then
Conte the right concentration will come
out of that because you don't again when
a person is committing to some practice
of concentration on account of the
muddled and foggy and obtuse thinking no
clarity of their thinking can arise why
because that that's basically the tools
they're using the development
concentration are the ones affected by
littles and if you're not seeing that
whatever you gain through them it's just
going to share the same nature
because people think that well as long
as I plan concentration of any kind that
will transfer itself and I'll benefit
from it in other like spiritual
development you want their development
did you think it's spiritual it's really
that central which is why yeah
most people's practice of spirituality
is very much central it's a practice of
sensuality
attaining physical experiences
exactly physical basically obtaining
agreeable experiences without trying to
see your motivation behind it or like
fully understanding the nature directs
those experiences and you could say that
any spiritual practice today it's
basically just spiritualizing sensuality
the true spiritual practice comes in you
undoing the sensuality and that's seeing
what they're already without you needing
to have a desire for it or inspiration
or whatever some sort of spiritual
uplifting that's why that's why if the
Dhamma is done rightly the Buddhist
teachings and rightly like nobody can
stumble upon it by accident or through
some miraculous experience it's done
through development it's achieved
through development and basically
hardwork that's what it was just
praising diligence self-reflection or
tolerating unwholesome states that you
know are present in you and you're
tolerating them by tolerating them you
give rise to motivation that's rooted in
them by giving rise to that sooner or
later gonna act out of it so you end up
being fully responsible for the
perpetuation of your own ignorance and
like to feel
there's not enough room his job visible
I'm gonna have one left
you know she's coming three